<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Baronnie van Breda</title>
            <author>Hondius, Hendrik, b. 1573.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104009</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4199</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4199)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1208:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Baronnie van Breda</title>
                  <author>Hondius, Hendrik, b. 1573.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 folded sheet ([1] p.) : engraved map  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Ten huyse van Henricus Hondius,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In s'Graven Haghe [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved by Hendrik Hondius.</note>
                  <note>With a pasted-on strip bearing letterpress English text: "A brief description of Breda, and the barronie thereof, represented in this mapp aboue".</note>
                  <note>Also issued, without the letterpress, in at least some copies of: Hexham, Henry.  A true and briefe relation of the famous seige of Breda: Delft, 1637.</note>
                  <note>London distribution conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3596 at eel 1196; number cancelled in STC (2nd ed.), and referred to STC (2nd ed.) 13685.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Breda (Netherlands) --  History --  Siege, 1624-1625 --  Maps.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:4199:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In s'Graven Haghe Ten huyse van Henricus Hondius, anno 1637.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>map of Breda drawn by Henricus Hondius</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <p>BARONNIE VAN BREDA</p>
                  <figDesc>inset map of the barony of Breda</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4199:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A <hi>BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF</hi> BREDA, and the Barronie thereof, repreſented in this mapp aboue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Cittie is a Land Towne, ſituated in a moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant place vpon two Riuers, the one called the <hi>Marck,</hi> the other the <hi>A,</hi> from whence the name thereof is deriued. For the <hi>A</hi> ſpreading it ſelf at the broadeſt in it, is called <hi>Breed A,</hi> that is, Broad A. This Riveret runing into it, doth ſtrengthen the Towne exceedingly, by feeding &amp; filling the moate with water, and within the Towne doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it ſelfe into the <hi>Marck.</hi> Jt is girt about with a thick, high, and a lofty wall, having rowes of Oakes, Elmes and other trees growing vpon it. The circuit of it is 4000 Geometricall paces at 5 foote, which make ſome three English miles in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, hauing twelue hundred Houſes in it, a goodly Markett place, and a faire Church, with a Lofly ſteeple 362 foote high. The Caſtle lies vpon the <hi>Marck</hi> with a goodly moate about it ſeuered from the Towne, a ſtately Orchard, and a Garden for pleaſure like a paradice, with a curious Maze, a fine proſpect, Fountaines, and other rarities in it.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is ſtrongly fortifyed with 13 Royall Bulwarkes, fiue large Hornworks, a broad &amp; a deepe moate in ſome places 200 foote ouer, diuerſe Ravelings Halfe-moones and a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skarfe, which J will delineate by Figure and Letter.</p>
            <div type="map_legend">
               <head>The Figure</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Js the Caſtle Bulwarke, Hom-worke and Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon which <hi>Count Harrie</hi> Governour of Frizeland runn his Approach.</item>
                  <item>2. Js Spite-Mansfeilds Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>3. The Boſch-Port-Bulwarck with the Horne-work and Raveling.</item>
                  <item>4. Maurice Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>5. Martins Bulwark with the Horne-worke.</item>
                  <item>6. Naſſaws Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>7. Ginnekens-Port-Bulwarke and Horne-worke vpon which his Highneſſe quarter Approached.</item>
                  <item>8. Notes Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>9. The Water-miles.</item>
                  <item>10. Hollands Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>11. Barnevelts Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>12. Anwerps-Port-Bulwark, and Horne-worke vpon which <hi>Count William</hi> ran his Approaches.</item>
                  <item>13. Lamberts Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>14. The new Bulwarke.</item>
                  <item>15. Heragiers Bulwarke, all theſe having Ravelings on the otherſide of the moate and Counterskarfe.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Deſcription of the ſeige, without and the ſeuerall quarters</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>A. His Highneſſe quarter conſiſting of English, French Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons and Dutches.</item>
                     <item>B. Count Williams quarter at the Hage.</item>
                     <item>C. Count Harries quarter Lord Gouvernour of Fryzeland at Tetering.</item>
                     <item>D. Coronell Varicks quarter neere Terheyde.</item>
                     <item>E. Lieutenant Coronell Boshuyſens quarter.</item>
                     <item>F. The Wallons quarter on the other ſide of the Marck.</item>
                     <item>G. Count Solmes his quarter.</item>
                     <item>H. The Lord of Brederodes quarter.</item>
                     <item>I. Coronell Ferens his quarter.</item>
                     <item>K. The Damme, where the Marck was ſtopped by his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe quarter.</item>
                     <item>L. The two firſt ſmall Redoubts to keepe in the Enemie vpon Ginnekens way into Breda.</item>
                     <item>N. The firſt Batterie, where the French and the English began their Approaches, the one on the right, and the other on the left hand.</item>
                     <item>N. The French Approach.</item>
                     <item>O. The English Approach.</item>
                     <item>P. A great Battery of 12 half Canon.</item>
                     <item>Q. A ſecond Batterie of 8 Peeces.</item>
                     <item>R. A third Batterie called the French Battery of 4 Peeces.</item>
                     <item>S. The Maſt, or Pine-wood through which the line of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvalation rann.</item>
                     <item>T. The Fort Papenmutch.</item>
                     <item>V. The Riveret A, betweene Papen-mutch the crowne worke, and the ſtone bridge.</item>
                     <item>W. Count Williams Approach from the Hagh.</item>
                     <item>X. Count Williams firſt Batterie made againſt Antwerpes Poort and Bulwarke.</item>
                     <item>Y. Count Harries Approach and Batterie vpon the Horne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke and Raveling before the Caſtle.</item>
                     <item>Z. The Houſe of pleaſure taken in by Count Harrie.</item>
                     <item>aa. This Arrable Lands.</item>
                     <item>bb. Low meddow grounds ouerflowne.</item>
                     <item>cc. The Pan-houſe and way towards <hi>Getruydenberke.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>dd. The high way towards <hi>Turnehout.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>ee. The high way towards <hi>Hooghstrate.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>ff. Js Rysbergen, where the Cardinall Jnfante quartered.</item>
                     <item>gg. Heuſenhout, or the way by which the Enemie marched through our gards when they departed.</item>
                     <item>hh. The Houſe of Knaverie moated.</item>
                     <item>ii. The States lodging.</item>
                     <item>kk. The black dyke.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
